Finding Aid for Earl V. Moore Papers 1870s-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Earl V. Moore papers 1870s-1987 1920s-1960s
Moore, Earl Vincent, 1890-1987.
The Earl V. Moore collection consists of the personal and professional papers of a noted musician, composer and director. Moore taught music at the University of Michigan from 1916 and served as director of the School of Music from1923 until his retirement in 1960.
89471 Aa 2 UAm
3 linear feet in 5 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Earl V. Moore's son, Dr. Vincent Moore (Donor No. 3723 ) in 1988 and 1990.
The collection is open for research.
Earl V. Moore was born September 27, 1890, in Lansing, Michigan, and was graduated from Lansing High School in 1908. In 1910, he received his Artist Diploma in Organ from the University of Michigan's University School of Music. He received his Bachelor of Arts degree in 1912 and his Master of Arts degree in 1916, also from the University School of Music. While completing his graduate degree, Moore was active in the school, becoming head of the Organ Department in 1914 and then appointed University Organist in 1915.
Moore was made an instructor in music and head of the Theory Department at the school in 1916, an assistant professor in 1919 and a full professor and director of the School of Music in 1923. From its establishment in 1881 until 1929, the University School of Music was technically a unit of the University Musical Society. In 1929, the School of Music became a unit of the University of Michigan but continued to be governed by its own Board of Directors. In 1940, the University Musical Society relinquished all rights and responsibilities of the School of Music to the University of Michigan, and the School of Music became an autonomous school within the University.
During the reorganization of the School of Music in the academic year 1939/40, Moore took a sabbatical leave to serve as the National Director of the Works Projects Administration Music Program. Upon his return in 1940, he resumed his position as director of the School of Music. In 1946, he was made dean and continued to serve in this position until his retirement from the University of Michigan in 1960.
In 1960 Moore joined the University of Houston as the M.D. Anderson Professor of Music and chairman of the Music Department. He remained there until 1970.
Moore was active in a number of organizations throughout his career. He was a member of the Executive Committee of the Music Teachers National Association from 1924 to 1926, serving as vice president in 1928 and president in 1936. He served as the president of the National Association of Schools of Music from 1932 to 1935. In addition, he was a member of the American Guild of Organists and of the music fraternity, Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia Fraternity of America. He was also a member of the Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Foundation from 1959 to 1972.
Moore, a well known composer, dedicated many of his works to the University of Michigan. His most famous work is "Varsity," written with J. Fred Lawton (class of 1911). Other compositions include "Voices of Michigan," "The Voyage of Arion" and "A Service of Invocation."
In appreciation of his distinguished career, Moore received many awards and honors. He was the recipient of honorary doctorate degrees from the University of Rochester in 1929, the American Conservatory of Music in 1938, and Drake University in 1945. In 1974, he was honored by the National Association of Schools of Music. On March 12, 1975, the new School of Music building at the University of Michigan was named the Earl V. Moore Building. An Earl V. Moore Scholarship Fund was begun in 1961 at the University of Michigan to assist music students with tuition and costs.
Earl V. Moore died on December 29, 1987.
The papers of Earl V. Moore document his career as professor and dean of the School of Music of the University of Michigan, as well as his career as a composer and performer. Though some of the papers and visual images date from the 1870s, the bulk of the collection dates from the 1920s through the 1960s. Consisting of three linear feet of papers and visual materials, the collection reflects Moore's many accomplishments as conductor, composer, lecturer, organist, and participant in professional societies.
The Moore papers have been divided into seven series: Biographical/Personal Materials, Correspondence, Topical Files, Newspaper Clippings, Musical Scores, Sound Recordings, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Carillons--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Frieze Memorial Organ.; Moore, Earl Vincent, 1890-1987.; Organs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Music.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Baird Carillon (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Choral Union.; Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Michigan Union Opera--1909.; Moore, Earl Vincent, 1890-1987.; Musicians.; Organs.; Phi Delta Theta Fraternity. Michigan Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); Sink, Charles A. (Charles Albert), 1879-1972.; Stanley, Albert A. (Albert Augustus), 1851-1932.; University of Michigan--Block M--1919.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.; University of Michigan. Junior Hop.; Dancing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Biographical/Personal Materials
  The series of Biographical/Personal Materials contains materials relating to Moore's personal and professional activities, including newsclippings, speeches, and programs from recitals and performances
  - General 1908-1988 (Box 1)
  - Family history (Box 1)
  - Honorary Degrees 1929-1970 (Box 1)
    (see also Photographs)
  - Programs 1913-1938
    - Retirement from University of Michigan 1955-1961 (Box 1)
      (includes UM Marching Band's Tribute to Moore, with photos)
  - Speeches 1923-1969, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is divided into two subseries, chronological and alphabetical. Of special interest in the chronological subseries is the correspondence from the years 1938-1940, a period of great transition for the School of Music. The second subseries of correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The majority of these correspondents are affiliated with the School of Music, and, therefore, the contents of their letters focus on School of Music activities.
  - Chronological
    - 1912, 1922-1937 (Box 1)
    - 1938-1940, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1941-1977 (Box 1)
  - Alphabetical (by correspondent)
    - Hoover, Earl H. ("Chick") 1927-1980 (Box 1)
    - Sink, Charles A. 1925 (Box 1)
    - Skinner, Ernest 1952-1959 (Box 1)
    - Stanley, Albert A. ("Dad") 1923-1930 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series is arranged alphabetically and documents Moore's activities as a professor, composer, and participant in professional organizations. Materials on the history of the School of Music, including an article written by Moore in 1957 for the Michigan Daily, are located in the "School of Music" folders. In the folder "Carillons" can be found information regarding Moore's selection of both the carillons for the University of Michigan as well as a bell for St. Andrew's Church in Ann Arbor. The folders "Works Projects Administration Music Program," "University of Houston," and the folders representing various organizations document Moore's professional activities outside the University of Michigan
  - Advisory Committee on the Arts, National Cultural Center 1959 (Box 1)
  - Carillons (UM) 1925-1936 (Box 1)
    (includes blueprints for bell in St. Andrew's Church, Ann Arbor)
  - Interlochen, University of Michigan Committee on Courses at 1930 (Box 1)
  - Lawton, J. Fred, and "Varsity," 1926-1964 (Box 1)
  - Music Teachers National Association 1935-1936, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ontario Music Teachers Association 1937 (Box 1)
  - Opera (UM) 1955-1975, undated (Box 1)
  - Organ, Frieze Memorial 1913-1977 (Box 1)
  - School of Music (UM)
    - General 1927-1977 (Box 1)
    - Albert Stanley's Notes for Music Literature and Music History Courses 1908-1921 (Box 1)
  - University of Houston 1961-1970 (Box 1)
  - Works Projects Administration Music Program 1939-1940, 1950 undated (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings
  The Newspaper Clippings series includes newspaper articles relating to Earl V. Moore's professional career as a musician, director and instructor.
  - 1910-1979, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Musical Scores (various)
  The Musical Scores series contains both printed and handwritten musical scores of works composed by Moore, including "Varsity" and "Voices of Michigan."
  - "Merry Mount" (Box 2)
  - "A Service of Invocation" (Box 2)
  - "Varsity" (Box 2)
  - "Voices of Michigan" (Box 2)
  - "The Voyage of Arion" (Box 2)
- Sound Recordings
  The Sound Recordings series consists of phonograph records and one reel-to-reel tape. Included is the program upon the occasion of the unveiling of the portrait of Earl V. Moore.
  - Phonograph records, 10 in.; 78 and 33 1/3 rpm
    - University of Michigan School of Music assorted recordings 1974-1979, undated, 5 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm 7.5 inches (Box 3)
    - "The Musician Comments," by Earl V. Moore undated, phonograph record disc (Box 3)
    - Album: "The Music of Michigan" (Box 3)
    - Disc: Side A, "The Yellow and the Blue"; Side B, College Days (song from "Koanzaland" co-written by EVM) (Box 3)
  - Reel-to-reel tape
    - "Dean Earl V. Moore Portrait Presentation," October 10, 1968, 56 minutes, 10 1/2 inches, 7 1/2 ips (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series include photographs and motion pictures relating to Moore, his career at the University of Michigan, family activities, and student life from the period when he was an undergraduate at the University. The films are both 16 and 8 mm. One of the more interesting films is of the Ann Arbor May Festival in the 1920s. This film has been digitized and is available for viewing. The other films are brief and mainly unidentified. These are currently unavailable for research use.
  - Photographs
    - Earl V. Moore (Box 4)
      - Elementary school class photo (4th Ward Grade School, Lansing, MI) circa 1900 (Box 4)
      - Honorary Degrees 1938-1964 (Box 4)
      - Portraits, 1902- circa 1960s (Box 4)
      - Informal photos, EVM with others; photos relating to EVM painting (Box 4)
      - Moore family, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - People affiliated with School of Music 1912-1958 (Box 4)
    - Professional Associations 1922, 1952 undated (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan
      - Carillon undated (Box 4)
      - Class of 1912 (Lit), reunion, 1952 (Box 4)
      - Dinner Honoring Moore 1960 (Box 4)
      - Football Spectators 1919, undated (Box 4)
      - Junior Hop 1911, 1912, 2 volumes (Folder 1)
        (photo albums from Phi Delta Theta fraternity's classes of 1912 and 1913)
      - "Koanzaland" (opening night), Whitney Theater December 1909 (Folder 1)
      - May Festival 1918 (Box 4)
      - Michigamua, reunion of 1912 "tribe" 1951 (Box 4)
      - Organ, Frieze Memorial 1913, undated (Box 4)
        (includes Hill Auditorium under construction)
  - Motion pictures
    - Film of 26th Ann Arbor May Festival 1920, [89471-1]
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 15 min
        Staff use only
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 5)
      - Streaming File: 89471-1, flv (Box 5)
    - Various short personal motion pictures (most unidentified) circa 1930s-1960s, 12 16 mm; 3 8mm films (Box 5)
      (include 25th anniversary "Varsity" band formation, 1936 and EVM faculty party, 1969)